<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Docs | Nissan Z32 Wiki</title><link>http://nissan-z32.allcars.wiki/docs/</link><atom:link href="http://nissan-z32.allcars.wiki/docs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Docs</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><image><url>img/map[gravatar:%!s(bool=false) shape:circle]</url><title>Docs</title><link>http://nissan-z32.allcars.wiki/docs/</link></image><item><title>Jacking up the Z</title><link>http://nissan-z32.allcars.wiki/docs/articles/technical/jacking_up/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://nissan-z32.allcars.wiki/docs/articles/technical/jacking_up/</guid><description>&lt;small>
&lt;p>&lt;em>From Z32 Wiki - &lt;a href="https://conceptzperformance.com/wiki/index.php/Jacking_Up_The_Z">https://conceptzperformance.com/wiki/index.php/Jacking_Up_The_Z&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/small>
&lt;p>The Z can be a difficult car to get into the air, and being that it&amp;rsquo;s so low, it&amp;rsquo;s pretty much essential for doing anything that&amp;rsquo;s under the car. This guide aims to help you get your car into the air safely and easily.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thanks to
&lt;a href="http://zhome.com/ZCMnL/PICS/jackUpCar/jackUpCar.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ZHome&lt;/a> for original pictures and info.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="tools-and-parts">Tools and Parts&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A 2-ton jack. Low profile jacks are highly preferred.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>2-ton jack stands.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>2x8&amp;rdquo; boards are extremely helpful.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Wheel chocks are also quite helpful.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>With lowered Zs, low-profile jacks and the 2x8&amp;rdquo; boards are practically a requirement.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="jack-points">Jack Points&lt;/h2>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/jacking_up/images/lift_points.jpg#no-margin" alt="*lift_points*">
&lt;h2 id="procedure">Procedure&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Caution:&lt;/strong> Never get under the vehicle when it is supported only by the jack. Always use safety stands to support the frame when you get under the vehicle.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="front">Front&lt;/h3>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Place your 2x8&amp;rdquo; boards in front of each wheel.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Drive up onto the boards. This raises the car 2&amp;rdquo; into the air, which makes all the difference in the world!&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/jacking_up/images/tire_over_2_x_8_plank_of_wood.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Tire_over_2_x_8_plank_of_wood*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Roll your jack under the car so that the handle is positioned between the tire and the fender/front bumper.&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/jacking_up/images/Inserting_the_jack_underneath_the_front_of_the_car.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Inserting_the_jack_underneath_the_front_of_the_car*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Position the jack head to meet with the front crossmember&amp;ndash;this is the structural piece that crosses under the engine oil pan. NOT the radiator support&amp;ndash;never lift the car from the radiator support!&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/jacking_up/images/jack_seat_underneath_suspension_cross_member.jpg#no-margin" alt="*jack_seat_underneath_suspension_cross_member*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Before you start jacking it up, ensure the parking brake is in, the car is in gear, and just for good juju, position some wheel chocks around the rear wheels.&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/jacking_up/images/wheel_chocks_around_rear_tire.jpg#no-margin" alt="*wheel_chocks_around_rear_tire*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Once the car is in the air, position your jack stands under the frame rails like so:&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/jacking_up/images/jack_stand_underneath_frame_rail.jpg#no-margin" alt="*jack_stand_underneath_frame_rail*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Relieve tension from the jack. If you&amp;rsquo;re only going to be working under the front, I tend to relieve a bit of tension from the jack, but leave it in position. If you&amp;rsquo;re continuing on to the rear, slowly and carefully lower the jack, making sure the jack stands are seating flatly. Remove the jack and head to the rear.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="rear">Rear&lt;/h3>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>If the car is already raised in the front, proceed to the next step. If not, position chocks around the front wheels before continuing.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Position the jack head under the rear differential and carefully raise it.&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/jacking_up/images/jack_seat_under_differential.jpg#no-margin" alt="*jack_seat_under_differential*">
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Once the car is in the air enough, place the jack stands at the jack points in the rear&amp;ndash;these are directly in front of the rear wheels.&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/jacking_up/images/rear_jack_stand_placement.jpg#no-margin" alt="*rear_jack_stand_placement*">
&lt;em>Note: If you&amp;rsquo;re jacking both the front and rear of the car up, make sure they are at even heights.&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Slowly lower the car onto the jackstands, making sure it lands evenly and without drama.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="pinch-welds">Pinch Welds&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In emergency situations, the included jack (in the tool box) can be used to raise the Z from the pinch welds (side of the car). However, this should be avoided if possible as it will virtually guarantee damage to the pinch welds.&lt;br>
Furthermore, NEVER raise the pinch-weld area where the frame meets the front fender &amp;ndash; this WILL cause damage.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Battery Relocation</title><link>http://nissan-z32.allcars.wiki/docs/articles/mods/battery_relocation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://nissan-z32.allcars.wiki/docs/articles/mods/battery_relocation/</guid><description>&lt;small>
&lt;p>&lt;em>From duanedibley.com -
&lt;a href="http://www.duanedibley.com/wordpress/cars/300zx/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">http://www.duanedibley.com/wordpress/cars/300zx/&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/small>
&lt;h2 id="warning--info">Warning &amp;amp; Info&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Before going any further it is important to say the following.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>this guide is for information only, there’s no warranty, implied or express that this is safe to do. This guide is for educational purposes only, nothing more&lt;/li>
&lt;li>do NOT put a standard battery in your trunk, they out gas many nasty things including  hydrogen gas (knock you out) and sulfuric gas (kill you) even when working normally.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>if you relocate the battery you should ONLY use a sealed battery, however even sealed batteries are only sealed when operating normally. If you over charge or abuse them they will also out gas and kill you. You should always use a vented to outside sealed box for them or a vent kit.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Nissan put the battery under the hood for good reasons, specifically because its vented to outside and can’t kill you there.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>In short if you aren’t sure what you are doing , then leave it alone.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I chose the
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000MSBUA4/ref=oh_aui_detailpage_o05_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Optima Yellow&lt;/a> battery for my Nissan, primarily because it is an AGM style sealed battery, tolerant of deep cycle discharge, and has duplicate terminals for maintenance charger connection even when disconnected from vehicle.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I chose to not put this in a sealed box but instead to fit a vent kit to get any fault condition out gassing to outside world. For what its worth this is acceptable to SCCA, so i consider it ok for street use also.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;em>SCCA rule 3.3.3.B&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>17) Any wet-cell battery moved from the manufacturer’s original location&lt;/em>&lt;br>
&lt;em>shall be in a non-conductive, marine-type container or equivalent and&lt;/em>&lt;br>
&lt;em>the “hot” terminal shall be insulated. All batteries (on-board power&lt;/em>&lt;br>
&lt;em>supplies) shall be attached securely to the frame or chassis structure&lt;/em>&lt;br>
&lt;em>independent of the marine-type container.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>&lt;strong>NOTE: This will allow the use of gel cell or dry cell (AGM) batteries without a non-conductive, marine-type container where applicable.&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>So relocating an AGM battery to the trunk area is generally safe (see above) but if the alternator regulator fails the alternator can then overvolt/overcharge the battery. in that case
&lt;a href="https://batteryuniversity.com/index.php/learn/article/health_concerns" target="_blank" rel="noopener">bad things&lt;/a> can happen&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Over-charging a lead acid battery can produce hydrogen-sulfide. The gas is colorless, very poisonous, flammable and has
the odor of rotten eggs. Hydrogen sulfate also occurs naturally during the breakdown of organic matter in swamps and
sewers; it is also present in volcanic gases, natural gas, and some well waters.&lt;br>
Being heavier than air, the gas accumulates at the bottom of poorly ventilated spaces. Although noticeable at first,
the sense of smell deadens with time and potential victims may be unaware of its presence.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To address this I also installed a
&lt;a href="">voltage monitor&lt;/a> in the driving area so i can see if the voltages rises too far&lt;br>
&lt;strong>I would recommend you do something similar.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="wire-choice">Wire Choice&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The options are:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>one wire or two&lt;/li>
&lt;li>what size or gauge wire&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Many people who seem to relocate the battery to the trunk advocate a single +12V wire from engine bay to trunk and ground the battery locally. This is the “one wire” solution.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The other option is to run two wires from engine bay to trunk for +12V and 0V connections and NOT ground battery locally in trunk. this is the “two wire” solution.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="sciencey-bit">“Sciencey” bit&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I’ll now explain why the two wire solution is the right choice, feel free to skip ahead if you disagree or don’t care why :-).&lt;br>
There are two concerns with relocating a car battery “further away” from where its needed.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Electrical interference to other components in the car.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The extra resistance of the cable will “loose” some of the battery voltage to IR losses in wires.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Electrical interference can occurs in two simple ways, capacitive and inductive coupling.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Capacitive coupling is an effect driven by voltage changes creating a”kick” on a victim wire from an aggressor wire
(our 12V battery supply) via capacitance between the wires. This is common within Silicon chips and where signals are
very small (RF receivers etc).
However even under maximum load (engine turning over for instance) the battery voltage will not change much and the
effect in cars will be minimal.
If needed You can “fix” this by shielding the aggressor wire.
Capacitive coupling is a “short range” effect.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Inductive coupling is an effect driven by  current changes creating a rapidly changing magnetic field, which creates a
“kick” on a victim wire.
Under maximum load or charging a car will see very large currents into and out of the battery creating large inductive
coupling effects.
This is a large range effect and normal shielding does not “fix” it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Inductive coupling is the major “interference” factor for cars and is the concern for battery relocation. 
Kirchoff’s law requires all “nodes” in a circuit to have a zero sum of currents, that means what goes in must come out !!!.
So when we are providing a large current out of the 12V battery terminal to drive the starter motor, the same current
MUST flow into the 0V terminal to compensate.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In a single wire solution the large starter/alternator current flow down the 12V wire, couples magnetically
to everything around it as the currents change.
The exact opposite return current flows through the car chassis to the local ground point then into the battery 0V terminal.
The result, maximum interference to anything along the 12V wire and “ground noise” for anything connected
to the chassis between the starter and battery.
When the battery is close to the starter and alternator, this effect is minimized but it shows when you relocate the battery to the trunk.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In a dual wire solution you have the same large currents in the 12V wire, but you now have the exact opposite current
(Kirchoff again) in the 0V wire returning to the battery.
If you carefully run the two wires together then the magnetic field of one exactly matches the magnetic field of the other,
but since the currents are opposite so are the fields.
And they cancel perfectly. No magnetic field means no coupling or interference.
There is still a strong field between the 12V and 0V wires but outside there’s nothing.
So minimal interference occurs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The down side of the two wire solution is that you have twice the resistance (two cables)
as the single wire solution if you assume the chassis connection is perfect (it isn’t).
So you need thicker cables and of course 2 of them.
As a general assumption a two wire solution will require 3x the space for wires compared to a one wire solution
to get same overall resistance and IR drop (i.e two wires each 1.4x larger diameter).&lt;br>
Referring to
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_wire_gauge" target="_blank" rel="noopener">this reference&lt;/a> if you use 3 gauge wire for a single wire solution
(0.64 mohms/m and 0.23inch/5.8mm diameter) you would need to use 1/0 gauge wire for a two wire solution ( 2x 0.32mohms/m and 2×0.32inch/8.2mm diameter).
For a 300 Amp starter current this would be about 0.8V drop and about 60 Watts of power loss or about 2% losses.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So we can all agree that if you can afford the space a two wire solution is best with the biggest cable you can fit 1/0 gauge in my case,
and no local ground connection in trunk, and that’s what i have done.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-plan">The Plan&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The plan is fairly simple&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>remove the battery from the passenger rear of engine bay and replace it with two connectors (+12v and gnd)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Run two 1/0 gauge wires from where battery used to be through fire wall and down passenger side of car to trunk area&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Remove the jack and tools from trunk&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mount battery on passenger side in trunk where tools used to be&lt;/li>
&lt;li>make cover for battery&lt;/li>
&lt;li>add some extra grounding cables in engine bay&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="materials">Materials&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>These are the materials I used, feel free to change, buy your favorite stuff&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B017VBMHRO/ref=oh_aui_detailpage_o05_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">SoundBox Connected 0 Gauge Red / Black Amplifier Amp Power/Ground 1/0 Wire Set 50 Feet SuperFlex Cable 25 Each, ANL Fuse Holder&lt;/a> $49.95&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B008D54QZE/ref=oh_aui_detailpage_o05_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">10 pcs Tinned Marine Grade Copper Battery Welding Cable Lug Connector Terminal&lt;/a> $9.05&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00WDOOGBA/ref=oh_aui_detailpage_o05_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">6 Gauge Premium Extra Flexible Welding Cable 600 VOLT – BLACK – 25 FEET&lt;/a> $8.00&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B01DCDL9WE/ref=oh_aui_detailpage_o07_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">InstallGear 0/2/4 AWG Gauge Power Distribution Block 1/0 Gauge In to (4) 4/8 Gauge Out&lt;/a> $9.95&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00P9NBN6S/ref=oh_aui_detailpage_o08_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">InstallGear 1/0 Gauge AWG Crimp Ring Terminals Connectors – 10-Pack (5 Positive, 5 Negative)&lt;/a> $ 13.83&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00L2SFEZA/ref=oh_aui_detailpage_o08_s01?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kicker GT2 Ground Termination Block with 1/0-8 Gauge Inputs&lt;/a> $13.80&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0194MSSMG/ref=oh_aui_detailpage_o09_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Raptor R5BT048P PRO SERIES – Positive Battery Terminal&lt;/a> $13.35&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00VPK3FGU/ref=oh_aui_detailpage_o08_s02?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Raptor R5BTN PRO SERIES – Negative Battery Terminal&lt;/a> $11.37&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000MSBUA4/ref=oh_aui_detailpage_o05_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Optima Batteries 8014-045 D34/78 YellowTop Dual Purpose Battery&lt;/a> $212.99&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0060YHYEK/ref=oh_aui_detailpage_o06_s01?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Schumacher BAF-STB Side Terminal Bolt&lt;/a> $5.39&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00CA9AB62/ref=oh_aui_detailpage_o07_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Billet Aluminum POLISHED Optima Battery Tray Holder Box&lt;/a> $55.00&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00RW5IKX0/ref=oh_aui_detailpage_o03_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CarbonX Carbon Fiber PLA 3D Printing Filament from 3DXTECH; 750g (1.65lbs), 1.75mm diameter&lt;/a> $39.95&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00DHGPVKI/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_search_asin_title?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Optima Digital 400 12V Performance Maintainer and Battery Charger – 150-40008&lt;/a> $103.58&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B01H3DKGFK/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_search_asin_title?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">KUMEED 12V DC 20A 30A 40A 50A 60A Car Audio Inline Circuit Breaker Fuse for System Protection (30A)&lt;/a> $10.99&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>3D printed items (STL provided)&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Panel mount for firewall to mount 2x Installgear Power Blocks&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Battery side terminal covers 2x&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Battery top terminal shields 2x&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bodywork Cable ties 12x&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Total Cost (excl tools)  $447&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="howto">Howto&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="relocate-the-battery">Relocate the Battery&lt;/h3>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Start with the 1/0 gauge cable, i got extra flexible because its got to bend a lot in some tight spaces. The wire itself is about 0.32 (wikipedia) inches diameter, but that’s without insulation. With insulation its 0.5 inches and with space for grommets etc we need 5/8 inch holes for it to pass through. i got 25ft of cable but that’s more than is required.&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/mods/battery_relocation/images/IMG_3559.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Battery cables*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the existing battery and dispose off&lt;br>
&lt;strong>YOU CAN’T USE THE ORIGINAL BATTERY IN THE TRUNK DUE TO OUT GASSING ISSUES&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the passenger fender. This is optional. I think you can do this with the front wheel removed and inner screen pulled back,
but it was just easier for me to remove the fender completely. &lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/mods/battery_relocation/images/IMG_3553.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Removed fender*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>There is a “flap” between the inner engine bay and the fender area adjacent to where the battery used to be the cables run through there. Run the cables into the engine bay here &lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/mods/battery_relocation/images/IMG_3554.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Flap Fender*">
&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/mods/battery_relocation/images/IMG_3561.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Flap Fender*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Next I mounted the two Install gear distribution blocks to the 3D printed panel that was then bolted to the firewall using the existing bolt and hole. Both 1/0 gauge wires connect on left.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>GND Block:&lt;/strong> I connected the starter cable directly to the dist block, and ran an extra 8 gauge wire from the dist block to the firewall ground mount. The two other 8 gauge cables are the additional engine bay grounding wires (see later)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>12V block:&lt;/strong> Connects to the original 12V cable, the original cable was “short” in my car so i extended it by 6 inches or so to reach. the second cable is the direct starter connection.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/mods/battery_relocation/images/IMG_3567.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Cable mounted*">
&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/mods/battery_relocation/images/IMG_3566.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Cable mounted*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Next is dealing with the firewall problem. There’s not too many options to get through the firewall on a  300ZX with such large cables, so holes will need to be drilled.
If you look in front of the passenger door hinge mounts you will see a hole right at bottom of the firewall bulkhead, this hole isn’t useful!! 
But if you drill holes about 2 inches above that then you get access to the interior ECU compartment.
I drilled 2x 5/8 inch holes side by side for the cables to accommodate both the cable and a grommet (per cable)&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/mods/battery_relocation/images/IMG_3557.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Cable holes*">
&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/mods/battery_relocation/images/IMG_3556.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Cable holes*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Inside the passenger foot well, remove the ECU cover (the wood one) and the kick panels.
I also unbolted the 3 relays hidden away inside the chassis frame to make space to “see”.&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/mods/battery_relocation/images/IMG_3558.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Relay*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>If you peer into the space behind the 3 relays you should be able to see “light” from the 2 holes you made.
Pass the cables through the holes onto the passenger foot well area (don’t forget the grommets).
Once the cables are through the relays can be returned to the chassis space.
I zipped tied them to keep them together as much as possible&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/mods/battery_relocation/images/IMG_3564.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Cable Install*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>The tedious bit is routing the cables along the floor on the passenger side all the way to the trunk area.
I used the 3D printed cable ties to zip tie the cables together and then double sided tape them to chassis.
The main objective is to keep the battery cables close to each other and consistent so that induced magnetic fields around them cancel cleanly.&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/mods/battery_relocation/images/IMG_3571.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Cable Install*">
&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/mods/battery_relocation/images/IMG_3568.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Cable Install*">
&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/mods/battery_relocation/images/IMG_3569.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Cable Install*">
&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/mods/battery_relocation/images/IMG_3570.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Cable Install*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>The battery tray holder was mounted in the trunk on the passenger side in the space previously occupied by the jack and tools.&lt;br>
It was bolted via 4 holes drilled in the floor through 4x 3/4 inch SS stand off’s, adjusted for length to get the base of tray “flat”.&lt;br>
The 12V fuse was mounted directly to the upper tray panel and the battery installed.&lt;br>
GND wire direct to the 0V battery terminal, 12V wire to the fuse and fuse to the 12V battery terminal with 3D printed shields under terminals to avoid shorts.
There is specifically &lt;strong>NO&lt;/strong> grounding of battery in trunk area. The NOCO battery maintainer cables were attached to the side terminals and 3D printed covers put over connections.&lt;/p>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/mods/battery_relocation/images/IMG_3572.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Battery Install*">
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Final build is to add the vent plumbing in case of over charge. This is &lt;strong>TBD&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Covers and making it “pretty” will come later&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="engine-bay-grounding">Engine Bay Grounding&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>There are a lot of perspectives and options regarding engine bay grounding , both if and how to do it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From
&lt;a href="http://forums.nicoclub.com/grounding-kit-myth-t585639.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">nicoclub.com&lt;/a> :&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>This is BS to me, especially the one I see here. So someone clear this up with science and not superfluous &amp;ldquo;feels&amp;rdquo; statements please&amp;hellip;even better documented evidence.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve gone all over the grounding kit I see on this forum as well as other sites and searches. All of them seems to be a bunch of excessive, unnecessary, over indulgent wiring.
You can&amp;rsquo;t get a flood through a straw, so why is everyone taking 16-14gauge wire and piping that to 4-0gauge wire all over the engine to a grounding point and saying its doing something.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The general theoretical principle of this is to provide a bigger gauge wire for a better return path, thus producing better cleaner electricity, and slightly higher voltage. However, the bigger gauge wire is always picking up from a smaller wire in these kits. A 14-16gauge wire going to a 4gauge to a grounding point. And also one grounding point to another. This doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense. If this was really suppose to do something, the 4gauge would HAVE to be coming directly from the source and not have an intimidiary wire in between. That to me defeats the purpose. Think about it, electricity is like water, if you take a 2&amp;rdquo; diameter pipe and feed that into a 15&amp;rdquo; diameter pipe, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t change the amount or force of water coming out the 15&amp;rdquo; as was coming out the 2&amp;rdquo;. And even reverse that and pour the 15&amp;rdquo; into the 2&amp;rdquo;; it would burn up the 2&amp;rdquo; because too much was being poured it. So why? How exactly does this grounding kit the way it is help?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I believe there is potential, however I&amp;rsquo;m not all the way sold, and definitely not the way this particular kit is designed and many others i see floating around. If I were to rewire the electrical system for better power all I would do is 3-5 wires.
1/ change the positive wire alternator to battery
2/ negative battery to chassis
3/ chassis to engine block
4/ the ecu if I have direct access&lt;/p>
&lt;p>4gauge standard, and 0-4gauge with aftermarket toys installed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All other points I don&amp;rsquo;t see a point to. And thus this can def be done way cheaper than this kit is being sold for(easily 50%)&amp;hellip;if this stuff actually makes a significant difference.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Philosophically its best to run as large a wire as you can from every point that wants a ground directly back to the battery terminal, no intermediate connections.
Practically this is difficult to do, especially if the battery is in the trunk.  
For me i have some specifics I want to address&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>ground both relay boxes to engine bay 0V terminal&lt;/li>
&lt;li>ground the engine block (so sensors have no issues)  to engine bay 0V terminal&lt;/li>
&lt;li>ground the throttle sensor to engine bay 0V terminal&lt;/li>
&lt;li>ground the temp sensors to engine bay 0V terminal&lt;/li>
&lt;li>ground the headlight ground points to engine bay 0V terminal.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>My engine bay 0V terminal has 2 free connections so i’ll use one for left and front of engine, one for rear and right of engine.  Direct connections are preferable but daisy chaining is a practical requirement. I’ll try to keep it to no more than 2 intermeadiate points and use gold plated tabs for those points if necessary.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I am not going to ground the alternator as long as the voltage across the two battery terminals in the engine bay indicate higher than static battery voltage i’ll assume the resistance of wires on the alternator 0v and 12v cables is not detrimental. Its possible that any alternator ground current through the block causes 0v noise that might impact the sensors on the block, so i might come back to this.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I am using 6 gauge wire with a mix of copper and gold crimp connectors.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I doubt that its possible to measure any differences  from before vs after, but since debugging grounding issues is a PITA i’d prefer to not have a problem.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="additional">Additional&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Subsequent to the relocation work, i added a sub woofer speaker into the car (under passenger area), and to support that i added a  2nd breaker circuit specifically for the subwoofer
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/mods/battery_relocation/images/breaker_hu44175b6db3225b1b427e270094c90790_64230_400x0_resize_q90_lanczos.jpg#no-margin" width="400" alt="*Circuit Breaker*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can see it added here
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/mods/battery_relocation/images/2019-04-19-11.03.06.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Circuit Breaker*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And to keep the battery in good shape if the car is not driven in a  while, i purchased an charger/maintainer specifically for this battery&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00DHGPVKI/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_search_asin_title?ie=UTF8&amp;psc=1">
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/mods/battery_relocation/images/charger_hu094babae42ad425e27cd25ba22529076_172411_400x0_resize_q90_lanczos.jpg#no-margin" width="400" alt="*Battery Charger*">
&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="left-to-do">Left to Do&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>What’s left to do is 3D print adaptors for the two vent holes on the battery so i can tube them to external. Its a “must do” item but not done yet&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>EGR Removal</title><link>http://nissan-z32.allcars.wiki/docs/articles/deletes/egr_removal/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://nissan-z32.allcars.wiki/docs/articles/deletes/egr_removal/</guid><description>&lt;small>
&lt;p>&lt;em>From Z32 Wiki - &lt;a href="https://conceptzperformance.com/wiki/index.php/EGR_Removal">https://conceptzperformance.com/wiki/index.php/EGR_Removal&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;br>
&lt;em>Images originally from
&lt;a href="http://ttzd.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">TTZD.com&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/small>
&lt;p>The &lt;strong>EGR (Exhaust Gas Recirculation) system&lt;/strong> is designed to introduce exhaust gas into the intake manifold&lt;br>
This lowers the combustion temperature to lower NOx emissions.&lt;br>
It is a required emissions control system, and removal of it is likely all kinds of illegal.&lt;br>
Here&amp;rsquo;s how to do it!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="tools-required">Tools Required&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Assortment of wrenches, ratchetss (10mm, 12mm and 14mm specifically).&lt;br>
Flex heads, ratcheting wrenches, stubbies, etc are all very helpful here.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Cutting tool (dremel tool) OR large prybar/ratchet straps.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A lot of patience.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="parts-required">Parts Required&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>EGR Bypass kit (available from your friendly neighborhood Z32 parts vendor).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="procedure">Procedure&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Removal of the EGR system is tricky, as it is in a very tight location.
There are two major hiccups associated with this job:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>The bolts that hold the EGR valve to the engine are longer than the space between the EGR valve and the firewall.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>The EGR tube that connects to the driver&amp;rsquo;s side exhaust manifold is extremely difficult to access.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>However, there are of course tricks and work-arounds for these problems. This article will hopefully explore these tricks.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="prerequisite">Prerequisite&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>You must first
&lt;a href="Intake_Manifold_Removal.html" title="Intake Manifold Removal">remove the intake manifold&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="engine-rocking-method">Engine-rocking Method&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>One common way to remove the intake manifold is performed when you have the transmission removed for another job (such as a clutch/flywheel replacement or upgrade).&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Spray all EGR bolts in PB Blaster and wait a day!&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>After removing the transmission, remove the upper intake pipes (2 for the NA, 4 for the TT). This will allow more flex in the engine on its mounts.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the vacuum line from the EGR valve (blue dot below).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the side-tube EGR bolts and, as much as you can, loosen the main EGR bolts (2 x 12mm, green dots). Break the tubes loose from the EGR.&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/deletes/egr_removal/images/EGR_valve_components.jpg#no-margin" alt="*EGR_valve_components*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Move the engine forward, away from the firewall, to gain more access to the EGR. Continue to loosen the EGR bolts until they&amp;rsquo;re all the way out. There are two main methods I&amp;rsquo;ve heard of doing this:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Putting down plenty of towels to protect the body work, run a ratchet strap from the engine (if you can find a good place to hook it onto) to a secured source, like a tree or a beam. With the parking brake in and the car in gear, ratchet the strap just enough to pull the engine forward and give you clearance to remove the bolts all the way.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Again, using plenty of padding, use a large pry-bar between the engine and the firewall to push the engine forward and away from the firewall, giving you clearance to remove the bolts. This one will likely require a partner.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the exhaust feed tube (pink dot above) fitting with a large adjustable wrench.
&lt;em>If you have trouble accessing it, remove the driver&amp;rsquo;s side water pipe (yellow dots)&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the exhaust feed tube fitting from the driver&amp;rsquo;s side exhaust manifold. This may require removal of the brake booster to access it. If you happen to have a RHD car, removal of the battery should be sufficient.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the EGR valve.&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/deletes/egr_removal/images/EGR_valve_removed.jpg#no-margin" alt="*EGR_valve_removed*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the EGR solenoid and associated vacuum lines.&lt;br>
Check out the
&lt;a href="../../technical/vacuum_diagrams" title="Vacuum Diagrams">Vacuum Diagrams&lt;/a> article for a little more help seeing how this is done.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Skip to the &amp;ldquo;Bypass Kit Installation&amp;rdquo; section below.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="bolt-cutting-method">Bolt-Cutting Method&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The other common method to removing the EGR valve is to cut the bolts at the rear of the engine.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Spray all EGR bolts in PB Blaster and wait a day!&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the vacuum line from the EGR valve (blue dot below).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the side-tube EGR bolts and, as much as you can, loosen the main EGR bolts (2 x 12mm, green dots). Break the tubes loose from the EGR.&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/deletes/egr_removal/images/EGR_valve_components.jpg#no-margin" alt="*EGR_valve_components*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>After loosening the main EGR bolts (2 x 12mm, two center green dots above), continue to loosen one until it&amp;rsquo;s touching the firewall, but still has to come out more. Using your cutting wheel, cut the bolt about 0.5&amp;rdquo; to 1.0&amp;rdquo; from the EGR valve.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Using vice-grip pliers, continue to remove the EGR bolt you just cut. If you it gets to the firewall again, cut some more off and repeat.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>After you get one bolt all the way out, repeat steps 4 and 5 for the other bolt. Doing one at a time allows you to have more &amp;ldquo;wiggle room&amp;rdquo; with the pliers.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the exhaust feed tube (pink dot above) fitting with a large adjustable wrench.
&lt;em>If you have trouble accessing it, remove the driver&amp;rsquo;s side water pipe (yellow dots)&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the exhaust feed tube fitting from the driver&amp;rsquo;s side exhaust manifold. This may require removal of the brake booster to access it. If you happen to have a RHD car, removal of the battery should be sufficient.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the EGR valve.&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/deletes/egr_removal/images/EGR_valve_removed.jpg#no-margin" alt="*EGR_valve_removed*">
se&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the EGR solenoid and associated vacuum lines.&lt;br>
Check out the
&lt;a href="../../technical/vacuum_diagrams" title="Vacuum Diagrams">Vacuum Diagrams&lt;/a> article for a little more help seeing how this is done.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Skip to the &amp;ldquo;Bypass Kit Installation&amp;rdquo; section below.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="bypassing-without-removal">Bypassing Without Removal&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Due to tool, time, or physical restraints, it&amp;rsquo;s sometimes impossible to remove the EGR system completely without removing the engine from the car. Many owners still opt to bypass the system, leaving much of it still in place but without function.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>After removing the plenum, install the plenum block plates on the underside of the plenum.&lt;br>
&lt;em>See the
&lt;a href="#bypass-kit-installation">Bypass Kit Installation&lt;/a> section below&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Using a cutting tool, cut the EGR tubes as far towards the back of the engine as possible.&lt;br>
Be sure to have any pipes (turbo outlets, for example) completely covered to prevent metal shavings from entering&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Install a rubber cap (5/8&amp;rdquo;?) on what&amp;rsquo;s left of the EGR tube. Use a zip-tie to secure it in place.&lt;br>
If the EGR valve is functioning properly, it will actually prevent exhaust gas from flowing through these if it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a vacuum signal, but this is still good practice, just-in-case.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Remove the EGR solenoid and associated vacuum lines.&lt;br>
Check out the
&lt;a href="../../technical/vacuum_diagrams" title="Vacuum Diagrams">Vacuum Diagrams&lt;/a> article for a little more help seeing how this is done.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="bypass-kit-installation">Bypass Kit Installation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>After removing the EGR system, it&amp;rsquo;s quite straightforward to install the delete/bypass kit.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Install the plenum block plates on the underside of the plenum, using the included gasket. Snug the bolts down to 6.2-8 lb-ft.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Using some high-temp anti-seize on the threads, install the manifold block-plug into the driver&amp;rsquo;s side exhaust manifold. Torque to 25-33 lb-ft.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Remove the EGR solenoid and associated vacuum lines.&lt;br>
Check out the
&lt;a href="../../technical/vacuum_diagrams" title="Vacuum Diagrams">Vacuum Diagrams&lt;/a> article for a little more help seeing how this is done. Most delete kits also include a vacuum nipple and zip tie, which can be used to block the vacuum port which used to run to the EGR solenoid from under the passenger side throttle body.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol></description></item><item><title>Intake Manifold</title><link>http://nissan-z32.allcars.wiki/docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://nissan-z32.allcars.wiki/docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold/</guid><description>&lt;small>
&lt;p>&lt;em>From Z32 Wiki - &lt;a href="http://conceptzperformance.com/wiki/index.php/Intake_Manifold">http://conceptzperformance.com/wiki/index.php/Intake_Manifold&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/small>
&lt;p>The &lt;strong>Intake Manifold&lt;/strong> (sometimes called the &lt;strong>plenum&lt;/strong>) is the main collector for the VG30DE(TT)&amp;lsquo;s intake system.&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold/images/300zx_intake_manifold_texture_black.jpg#no-margin" alt="*A black powder-coated intake manifold*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="function">Function&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The intake manifold houses the throttle bodies which vary the amount of air entering. It also carries the task of distributing air evenly to each cylinder, and providing vacuum signal for various auxiliary components.&lt;br>
A great deal of effort was focused on the design of the intake manifold, especially in the shape of its intake runners. The following excerpt from AutoSpeed&amp;rsquo;s
&lt;a href="http://www.autospeed.com/A_109870/cms/article.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">article on the VG30DETT&lt;/a> explains:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;em>The intake system design had to balance two opposing outcomes:&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;em>the smaller that the intake runner diameters were made, the greater the frictional losses (and so pressure drops)&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>but the larger the intake runner diameters, the slower the airflow speed, resulting in a decrease in cylinder filling, especially at low rpm&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;em>In addition, simulation and testing showed that long intake runners resulted in better torque development at low engine revs - however, fitting long runners into an already crowded engine bay was going to be difficult. Runners that were 360mm long gave peak intake efficiency at 4400 rpm, while lengthening these to 480mm dropped the peak intake efficiency revs to 3600 rpm. Since one of the goals of the engineers was strong bottom-end torque, the longer runners became a requirement. Further testing showed that a runner diameter of 48mm worked well with the 480mm long design.&lt;/em>&lt;br>
&lt;em>[It&amp;rsquo;s interesting to note the major amount of development that occurred in tuning the intake system in this turbocharged engine. Many turbo engines - including Nissan&amp;rsquo;s own RB26DETT Skyline GT-R engine - have no intake resonance tuning at all.]&lt;/em>&lt;br>
&lt;em>Once 480mm (nearly 19 inch!) long intake runners had been decided upon, the next question was how they&amp;rsquo;d be fitted under the bonnet. The previous model VG30DE had placed the plenum chamber centrally on top of the V6, with relatively short but direct runners connecting the plenum to the intake valves. The measured pressure drop with this arrangement was 85 units.&lt;/em>&lt;br>
&lt;em>[The units used are not completely clear - they may be mm of water at 4.4 cubic metres/minute flow.]&lt;/em>&lt;br>
&lt;em>The first prototype VG30DETT intake system design placed a plenum chamber above each bank of cylinders, with the intake runners for that head connected to the plenum above it. This required that each runner go through nearly a U-turn, and so was called the &amp;lsquo;U-turnport&amp;rsquo; design. The pressure drop of this design was, however, very high - being measured at 105 units, or nearly 24 per cent higher than the original VG30DE design with the centrally-located plenum chamber.&lt;/em>&lt;br>
&lt;em>A &amp;lsquo;crossport&amp;rsquo; design was then built, where the plenum chamber feeds the opposite cylinder bank. This design allowed the retention of the long intake runners but gave a measured pressure drop of only 80 units - better than the VG30DE design, despite the use of intake runners nearly twice as long. The change from a U-turnport to a crossport design resulted in a 5 per cent increase in peak power.&lt;/em>&lt;br>
&lt;em>The intake system ahead of the intake manifold was also extensively developed. The airfilter housing used two filtering elements to provide sufficient filtering area within the tight confines of the engine bay. Only a single airflow meter was used, but the junction where the duct splits to feed each turbo was extensively developed. The final design used a very long radius inner bend reducing measured pressure drop by 77 per cent over some of the designs trialled. Together with the use of a bellmouth at the entrance to the airflow meter, these flow improvements increased peak power by 2 per cent.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="versions">Versions&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There are two versions of the intake manifold used on the 300ZX, Phase I and Phase II.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>&lt;/th>
&lt;th align="center">&lt;strong>Non-Turbo&lt;/strong>&lt;/th>
&lt;th align="center">&lt;strong>NA (Convertible)&lt;/strong>&lt;/th>
&lt;th align="center">&lt;strong>Twin Turbo&lt;/strong>&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Phase I&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="center">1990-1992&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="center">1993&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="center">1990-1994&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;strong>Phase II&lt;/strong>&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="center">1993-1996&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="center">1994-1996&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="center">1995-1996&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>Phase I and Phase II manifolds &lt;em>are&lt;/em> interchangeable. The only difference between the two are throttle spring cover mounting points on the Phase II manifolds.
The Z32 never actually came with such covers, but the Infiniti J30 did (which used the same intake manifold as the P2 Z32).&lt;br>
NA and TT manifolds are also identical; the only differences being the port fittings and balance tube &lt;em>attached&lt;/em> to the manifold.
The same holds true for RHD and LHD Zs.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="related-articles">Related Articles&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="../intake_manifold_removal" title="Intake Manifold Removal">Intake Manifold Removal&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Intake Manifold Removal</title><link>http://nissan-z32.allcars.wiki/docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold_removal/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://nissan-z32.allcars.wiki/docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold_removal/</guid><description>&lt;small>
&lt;p>&lt;em>From Z32 Wiki - &lt;a href="https://conceptzperformance.com/wiki/index.php/Intake_Manifold_Removal">https://conceptzperformance.com/wiki/index.php/Intake_Manifold_Removal&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/small>
&lt;p>Removal of the
&lt;a href="../intake_manifold" title="Intake Manifold">Intake Manifold&lt;/a> (also called the &lt;strong>plenum&lt;/strong>) is necessary or helpful to perform several jobs on the VG30DE(TT), such as:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Fuel Injector Replacement (as an alternative to the
&lt;a href="../wiki/index.php/Dremel_Method" title="Dremel Method">Dremel Method&lt;/a>).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Valve Cover re-seal.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>PCV reroute/delete.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Throttle Body Coolant line bypass/removal.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>EGR bypass/removal.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Cylinder head work (replacement, lifter removal, cam replacement, etc).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The most common reason to remove the intake manifold is to replace one or more faulty fuel injectors, and other jobs are usually performed at the same time due to the amount of labor required to remove the intake manifold. While it can be done in less than an hour (especially after doing various deletes/bypasses), it involves removal of multiple engine technologies, from coilpacks and vacuum lines, to fuel lines and EGR tubes. This is often intimidating for owners, and is often considered to be a much harder job than many feel it actually is. If you&amp;rsquo;re new at this, bag and label &lt;strong>everything!&lt;/strong>. In any case, a handy guide with pictures makes everything easier!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Pictures and info from this article are a combination of those from NytWolf, those found on the Tech section of Aus300ZX, and various other sources (including my own noggin). A huge thanks goes out to the original photographers and writers for the work they put into making these writeups, which have saved headaches for hundreds of Z owners.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="recommended-parts">Recommended Parts&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Intake Manifold Gasket (upper plenum to lower plenum) (Part #14033-30P02). &lt;strong>Required.&lt;/strong> This is a paper gasket that is destroyed upon removal and &lt;em>must&lt;/em> be replaced. OEM Nissan is recommended (and is very cheap).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Balance tube O-ring set (if they haven&amp;rsquo;t been replaced yet).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="tools-needed">Tools Needed&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>8mm, 10mm, 12mm, 12mm (deep) sockets.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ratcheting driver for sockets.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Flex joint (U-Joint) and various extensions HIGHLY recommended.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>8mm, 10mm, 14mm wrenches (stubby wrenches and ratcheting wrenches are also very helpful).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>5mm Allen wrench.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Long needle nose pliers.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Philips &amp;amp; Flathead screwdrivers.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dental pick set is helpful for various electrical connectors.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Hose removal pliers &lt;em>rock&lt;/em> for this.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="procedure">Procedure&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="upper-components">Upper Components&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The image below will be used as supplemental reference for the following steps.&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold_removal/images/plenum.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Plenum*">
&lt;br>
We&amp;rsquo;ll start by concentrating the components on and around the top of the intake manifold.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Relieve fuel pressure from the system (
&lt;a href="../fuel_pressure_relief" title="Fuel Pressure Relief">Fuel Pressure Relief&lt;/a>)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove throttle cable cover (Item &lt;strong>3&lt;/strong>) (green dot; 4x5mm Allen bolts).&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold_removal/images/cable_cover.jpg#no-margin" alt="*cable cover*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Slightly loosen 14mm bolts holding the throttle cable and cruise control cable to the bracket on the upper plenum.&lt;br>
You may have to remove some little bracket guides (10mm bolts) that bind the cables to the plenum.&lt;br>
The cruise control can optionally be removed, but I&amp;rsquo;ve found you can just gently flex the cables out of the way. The wiper blades do a good job holding them down.&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold_removal/images/linkage.jpg#no-margin" alt="*linkage*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Disconnect all vacuum lines attached to the balance tube (yellow dots pictured below).&lt;br>
It may be helpful to label them&amp;ndash;tape and a marker work well.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the 3x12mm nuts and 2x12mm bolts holding the balance tube to the plenum (green dots below).
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold_removal/images/balance_tube.jpg#no-margin" alt="*balance tube*">
&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold_removal/images/balance_tube_02.jpg#no-margin" alt="*balance tube*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the large vacuum lines that run to the brake booster and clutch booster (on M/T TT Models) (Items &lt;strong>6&lt;/strong>).
Also remove the vacuum line from the front barb fitting (the one leading to the clutch booster on applicable models).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>There is a tube that runs from the driver&amp;rsquo;s side accordion pipe to the IACV at the back of the plenum (Item &lt;strong>14&lt;/strong>).&lt;br>
Remove the 10mm bolt securing it to the plenum. Loosen its hose clamps (at the accordion pipe and where it meets the IACV) and remove this pipe assembly.&lt;br>
&lt;em>It may be necessary to remove the barb fittings for the clutch and brake boosters that attach to the plenum in order to remove this pipe&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Loosen the hose clamp for the Air Regulator Hose at the back/center of the Balance Tube. Remove this hose.
&lt;em>If you can&amp;rsquo;t get this hose off, don&amp;rsquo;t sweat it&amp;ndash;you can pull away from it while removing the balance tube, which makes it much easier&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Disconnect the fuel lines that go from the Fuel Dampener to the Fuel Rail, and from the Fuel Rail to the FPR (circled in red).&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold_removal/images/hoses_to_remove.png#no-margin" alt="*hose to remove*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the bolts that hold the Fuel Dampener and Fuel Pressure Regulator to the plenum. (2x10mm for each).&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold_removal/images/fuel_pipe_01.jpg#no-margin" alt="*fuel pipe*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the 3x10mm bolts that secure the upper fuel gallery to the plenum. Remove the fuel gallery.&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold_removal/images/fuel_gallery.jpg#no-margin" alt="*fuel gallery*">
&lt;br>
&lt;em>I tend to leave the two main hoses (feed and return) connected to the fuel gallery and simply flex them and set the gallery off to the side. To be extra cautious, feel free to remove these hoses and the fuel gallery completely. Be aware that fuel can quickly damage paint, so keep this in mind when fiddling with the fuel gallery.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Disconnect the electrical connectors for the six coilpacks (yellow dots below).&lt;br>
Remove the coilpack wire guides (philips screw head, blue dot) and, if necessary, the oil cap (red dot).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the 12x12mm bolts (2 each; green dots below) that secure the coilpacks to the plenum. Remove the coil packs.&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold_removal/images/coil_pack_01.jpg#no-margin" alt="*coil pack*">
&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold_removal/images/coil_pack_02.jpg#no-margin" alt="*coil pack*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the injector connectors from each of the six fuel injectors.&lt;br>
This is where your dental pics come in handy (if you have Phase 1 injectors).
&lt;em>If you lose the little spring clips, don&amp;rsquo;t worry. You can recover them once you get the plenum off, and many don&amp;rsquo;t run them at all&amp;ndash;a small dab of RTV on the flat (non-electrical) face of the component will help secure the connectors.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the connectors to the IACV components (more dental pick mayhem):&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>AAC (Yellow connector)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>FICD (Blue connector)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Air Regulator (Blue Connector)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Disconnect the TPS (spring clip at the front, regular oval connector at the pigtail)&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold_removal/images/tps_01.jpg#no-margin" alt="*tps*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the two ground wires (1x10mm bolt each).&lt;br>
One is near the rear passenger side of the plenum. The other is near the rear driver&amp;rsquo;s side.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Flex the wiring harness up and out of the way.&lt;br>
I also tend to use the wiper blades to hug this to the windshield and keep it out of my face.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Go take a break!&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="intake-pipes">Intake Pipes&lt;/h3>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the throttle intake pipes.
These are the two pipes that connect directly to the throttle bodies. Plug these pipes.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>TT Models: remove the front turbo outlets.&lt;br>
These are the &amp;ldquo;outer&amp;rdquo; intake pipes that run from the turbo outlets to the intercoolers. Plug these pipes.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>TT Models: On each side of the plenum are &amp;ldquo;support brackets&amp;rdquo; that connect the intake manifold to the heads, and each have a 10mm bolt (blue dot) connecting the turbo outlets.
Remove these two bolts. Also remove the two 12mm bolts (orange dots) securing this bracket to the plenum.&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold_removal/images/intake_pipes.jpg#no-margin" alt="*intake pipes*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>TT Models&lt;/strong>: Grab a stubby screwdriver and loosen the upper hose clamp that secures the turbo outlet pipes to the rubber couplers on the turbochargers.&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold_removal/images/turbo_outlets.jpg#no-margin" alt="*turbo outlets*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>TT Models&lt;/strong>: Remove the turbo outlet pipes. Plug these openings.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="drivers-side">Driver&amp;rsquo;s Side&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s concentrate on some components on the driver&amp;rsquo;s side for a bit.&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold_removal/images/engine_left.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Engine Left*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Loose and slide-off the hose clamp for the PCV hose (Item &lt;strong>1&lt;/strong>).&lt;br>
If you plan on replacing these hoses, cut that shit off.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the throttle body coolant lines (Items &lt;strong>2&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>3&lt;/strong>).&lt;br>
If you are doing the coolant line bypass (&lt;strong>highly recommended&lt;/strong>), save yourself some trouble and just cut these hoses.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the bolts (2x10mm) securing the EGR feed line to the plenum underside.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Remember earlier when I said to plug the pipes you removed? Make sure it&amp;rsquo;s done! These EGR bolts are &lt;strong>notorious&lt;/strong> for falling into the turbo inlet pipe.*&lt;/li>
&lt;li>These are a total bitch to remove, but play around with different combinations of extensions, swivel joints/flex joints, stubby wrenches, etc, and find what works for you.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="passenger-side">Passenger Side&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Moving over to the passenger side&amp;hellip;&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold_removal/images/engine_right.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Engine Right*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the throttle body coolant line (not labeled above, but it&amp;rsquo;s in the same position as on the driver&amp;rsquo;s side).
&lt;em>If you&amp;rsquo;re doing the coolant line bypass (highly recommended), just save yourself the grief and cut these off.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Loosen the hose clamp for the PCV hose (Item &lt;strong>8&lt;/strong>). If you&amp;rsquo;re replacing the PCV hose, just cut the old one.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the rear coolant line (on turbo models) (item &lt;strong>9&lt;/strong>).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the EGR tube (item &lt;strong>7&lt;/strong>).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="rear-side">Rear Side&lt;/h3>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold_removal/images/engine_rear.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Engine Rear*">
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the hose clamp for the rear driver&amp;rsquo;s side coolant line (Item &lt;strong>10&lt;/strong>).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the hose clamp for the rear passenger&amp;rsquo;s side coolant line (item &lt;strong>11&lt;/strong>).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove these two lines. If you&amp;rsquo;re doing the coolant line bypass, just cut them.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Disconnect the EGR vacuum line (item &lt;strong>12&lt;/strong>).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="upper-plenum">Upper Plenum&lt;/h3>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Remove the main upper plenum bolts.&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold_removal/images/plenum_upper.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Upper Plenum*">
&lt;br>
&lt;em>Regular bolts (green dots) are all the same. Red dot is the short one, and orange dot is the hex-head one (which doubles as a mounting point for the throttle cable cover).&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Carefully lift the plenum up directly away from the engine. If you left the PCV hoses connected, allow the rear to tip back towards the engine.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Making sure there are no snags, electrical connectors, hoses, etc still hanging on, pull the plenum towards the front of the engine. If you left the PCV hoses connected, pull the plenum away to help pull the PCV hoses off the PCV valves on the plenum. It helps to have a partner with this!&lt;br>
&lt;em>When handling the intake manifold, be careful not to damage the TPS or IACV.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Plug the lower intake manifold ports (6).&lt;br>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/intake_manifold_removal/images/lower_intake_manifold.jpg#no-margin" alt="*Lower Intake Manifold*">
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Go take a break!&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="post-removal-jobs">Post-Removal Jobs&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There are a few different jobs that can be completed when the intake manifold has been removed. Now that it&amp;rsquo;s done, check out the guides for some of these jobs:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="../wiki/index.php/Coolant_Line_Bypass" title="Coolant Line Bypass">Coolant Line Bypass&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="../../deletes/egr_removal" title="EGR Removal">EGR Bypass/Removal&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="../wiki/index.php/PCV_Reroute" title="PCV Reroute">PCV Reroute&lt;/a> or
&lt;a href="../wiki/index.php/PCV_Delete" title="PCV Delete">Delete&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="../wiki/index.php/Fuel_Injector_Replacement" title="Fuel Injector Replacement">Fuel Injector Replacement&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;a href="../wiki/index.php/Valve_Cover" title="Valve Cover">Valve Cover Re-seal&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>At the very least, it is &lt;strong>highly&lt;/strong> recommended that you complete the &lt;strong>coolant line bypass&lt;/strong>.&lt;br>
This makes future plenum pulls &lt;em>much, much&lt;/em> easier, in addition to eliminating multiple points for potential coolant leaks.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="re-installation">Re-installation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Aside from any deletes/bypasses completed, installation of the plenum is the reverse of the removal. Be careful when installing the new plenum gasket as it&amp;rsquo;s paper and easily damaged, and ensure that the gasket mating surfaces are clean and totally flat.&lt;br>
The torque specs needed for reinstallation are as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Plenum bolts: 12-15 lb-ft (do in a spiral pattern starting from the center).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Side braces: Approx 6-8 lb-ft.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Balance tube nuts and bolts: 12-15 lb-ft.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>EGR bolts: 6.2-8 lb-ft.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Vacuum Diagrams</title><link>http://nissan-z32.allcars.wiki/docs/articles/technical/vacuum_diagrams/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://nissan-z32.allcars.wiki/docs/articles/technical/vacuum_diagrams/</guid><description>&lt;small>
&lt;p>&lt;em>From Z32 Wiki - &lt;a href="https://conceptzperformance.com/wiki/index.php/Vacuum_Diagrams">https://conceptzperformance.com/wiki/index.php/Vacuum_Diagrams&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/small>
&lt;p>These diagrams illustrate the vacuum system in the Z32.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="naturally-aspirated">Naturally Aspirated&lt;/h2>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/vacuum_diagrams/images/na-diagram.png#no-margin" alt="*NA diagram*">
&lt;h2 id="twin-turbo">Twin Turbo&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="stock">Stock&lt;/h3>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/vacuum_diagrams/images/twin-turbo-stock.png#no-margin" alt="*Twin Turbo Stock diagram*">
&lt;h3 id="modified">Modified&lt;/h3>
&lt;img src="../docs/articles/technical/vacuum_diagrams/images/twin-turbo-modified.png#no-margin" alt="*Twin Turbo Modified diagram*"></description></item></channel></rss>